[Music]
hi everyone this is Ravi welcome to
tricentis TSA Advanced Training
tutorial so this is our lesson 12 if
you compare with the Advanced
Training and this is our lesson 27 if
you consider it as an overall triena
training so in this lesson I'm going to
teach you how can we use if then
conditional statements by using trient
tasa while automating your test
cases when you create if statements TSA
will automatically create a then
statement along with the condition
object so you can also create an else
statement via the context menu of if
statements if required so adding El
statement is an optional or you can add
this L statement by left clicking the if
statement and selecting create object
else statement from the dynamic menu
test
cases so if the condition is fulfilled
the test steps are executed once in the
then statement if the condition is not
fulfilled then the test steps are run
once in L
statement so what is the order of
conditions if you see the sequence first
if comes and then second condition
within the if
statement later then within the if
statement and then else it's an optional
so now let's jump onto the system and
see how can we automate test cases by
using trient TSA with if then
conditional statements so this is my
TSA right what I did I just created a
new folder
here called
Lesson 12 if then statements correct and
then I've created another a test case
called I just created a test case right
and then I renamed it as if then test
case right so first before you automate
your test case let us understand what is
the test scenario that we are going to
automate by using IF then condition okay
so as usual we are going to navigate to
web demo shop okay demo web shop okay so
what I'm going to do see when
you navigate to demo webshop
if login link is visible then you click
on login and then perform
login in case in case let's say once I
login Okay click on login if in case I
close the browser
without log out right I close the
browser without log out then what
happens we'll see see as soon as you log
in I mean as soon as you enter the
URL the session is
still showing you that means you already
logged in so now I want to automate a
scenario where if login link is visible
then directly perform login if login is
not visible then what does it
mean the user is already login so now I
want to perform if login is not visible
then I want to click on log out and then
I want to click on login and then I want
to login right so let us see how can we
automate this okay so now if you see I
have already arranged my modules right
side okay so here first you need to
insert your if statement how right click
on your test case and then insert create
if statement select this option okay
if this one if what is the condition
here I want to test so let us do one
more thing okay before I enter the
condition and then what what to do I
want to introduce L statement also how
can we do that again right click here if
you see here I have a create El
statement If You observe
closely your if statement then it is
showing left side Arrow your else
statement showing right side Arrow okay
so now if what is the condition my first
condition is if login link presents
correct
so here if you see this is my top menu
okay just drag this and drop
here if what is the condition I'll say
login visible if login visible right so
what I will do here login what I'm going
to do here I'm going to select visible
if this is visible true
right
then this is your condition you
specified your condition now what action
to be performed I want to click on login
so again drag this drop menu top menu
and drop it here and what is the action
I want to click on then click login I'm
just renaming the step Okay click login
so what I'm going to do here I'm simply
enter the value as input done
save this now else statement what is our
else statement if login is not present
that means user is already logged in
right first you need to log out okay so
for that again here L statement I'm
going to drag this and drop
here so if login is not visible that
means you
are already logged in correct so so here
what I'm going to do I'm
simply going to log
out okay login is not visible means log
out should be present and then I'm going
to click on login now drag and drop into
L statement itself
okay log out and then login click on
login right but here again
here if you see once you click on login
in both the statements if login is
visible I'm just clicking on login but
along with that I want to enter
my username and password correct so
that's why I'm going to to Simply drag
this and then drop it
here I want to enter my username and
password correct I can simply provide my
username
right and then provide your
password right and then you click on
login so you can simply copy this same
step here
if login does not visible then it goes
to L statement right it's going to log
out and then it's going to click on
login and then you're going to
perform
entering your username and password so
now let us first run our first condition
okay let us do one thing I already
logged out that means when I launch this
application your login is visible that
means if statement should execute else
statement should not execute okay let's
run this right click and run in
scratchbook so now let's see what
happens it should click on
login oh I think we forgot one thing
here okay let's close this let's uh stop
here okay because when we are verifying
right we forgot to specify it as verify
so what is the condition first condition
I need to check if that is visible so if
you see here here is visible I'm need to
verify this I need not to input this I
need to verify that okay so now again
let's run this right click and run in
scratchbook now it should see if login
is visible so in this case login is
visible that means it's going to
directly click on login button yes it
clicked on login link and then it should
enter your username password done now if
I
execute the test case again now because
you already logged in right it should go
to to else condition it should execute
your else condition
not if condition if condition will be
false because login will not be visible
it goes to else condition then it should
perform log out and then login okay
let's execute again this one without log
out okay run
this see now now login will not be
visible for TSA and then it enters the
else
it should log
out right so it's going to log out
now yeah it's logged out and then again
it's going to click on login see and
then it's going to enter your username
and
password perfect so that means now our
if else condition is working
successfully right if you see
here the first condition does not matter
right it went to Second condition else
condition and everything is
passed okay hope you all understand the
concept of if then conditional
statements and how can we use if then
conditional statements in trient tasa
while automating your test
cases please do subscribe to the channel
click on Bell icon you'll receive
notifications whenever I publish more
videos thank
[Music]
you